ARUN VARGHESE

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER - PLANO, TX

OVERVIEW

Software Engineer with over 10 years of full-stack experience in the complete development life cycle of distributed web applications, from design to development to delivery. In my free time, I work on front-end web development with popular frameworks to learn more about UI/UX and Software Architecture. View my online resume for details →

QUALIFICATIONS

- √ 10+ years of java development experience using agile methodology
- ✓ Strong technical and interactive communication skills, excellent collaboration skills
- Client-focused, interested in working with scalable technology to solve business problems
- ✓ Flexible and capable of performing well on team-oriented tasks and meeting deadlines
- Effective leadership skills with respect to influencing team members and delegating abilities
- √ Adaptable and successful in handling multiple responsibilities in high-stress environments
- Exceptional job at maintaining relationships with business/customers, vendors, and stakeholders
 Proactively analyzes and recommends ways to reduce technical debt and automate repetitive tasks
- ✓ Able to drive delivery of complex projects with distributed teams, managing time and resources effectively
- Writes scalable and resilient code by utilizing emerging technology and researching latest software patterns

EXPERIENCE

Senior Full Stack Software Engineer

January 2022 - Present

Comcast - Plano, Texas

- Designed and developed reusable angular material components to streamline development of new features and provide consistency for the look and feel of internal and external web applications
- Proficiently troubleshooted complex issues across multilayered architecture and documented solutions to reduce repetitive investigations and improve triage times for support teams by 20%
- Identified and revamped workflow tool search/filtering by implementing enhancements like server-side pagination to improve page load performance from 10+sec to <2sec</p>
- Partnered with DevOps team to get Spring Boot instance of legacy webservice into Production in a timely manner to improve stability, streamline deployments, and debugging
- Migrated manual processes and form submissions to self-service digitized forms to increase customer onboarding throughput by 10x

Senior Software Engineer & Technical Lead

June 2018 - December 2021

Masergy, Inc. - Plano, Texas

- Decomposed company sales workflow by domains, took isolated contexts and migrated them to micro services that are a part of a new event driven messaging architecture
- Implemented versioned APIs and bounded contexts using DTOs and JPA to reduce dependencies, remove cross-schema communications, improve scalability, and properly define domains
- Leveraged front-end expertise to successfully migrate legacy application pages to Angular, thus reducing page load times, improving maintainability, and enriching the customer experience
- Designed and developed solution for persisting user application preferences through a micro service using a mongo data store; presented during company hackathon and was approved for implementation
- Organized lunch and learn on Angular practices, standards, and problems/solutions, providing the team with a collaborative atmosphere while increasing knowledge and promoting work culture

Senior Software Engineer

August 2015 – June 2018

Spireon, Inc. - Irving, Texas

- Focused on our core platform, taking part in solution design and implementation of RESTful web services as part of a push for a more micro service-oriented architecture using Spring Boot, Kafka, JPA, and Docker
- Managed onboarding for new team members, including mentorship and best practices. In addition, managed ongoing relationships with major carriers like Sprint/T-Mobile/Verizon/AT&T
- Worked on internal tool development, vendor API integrations for M2M architecture, and UI/UX enhancements while successfully collaborating with distributed teams to drive consistent feature delivery
- Owned the development and successful rollout of SIM management features for new vendors/partners, which decreased device airtime costs up to fifty percent and support team's involvement in the process
- Collaborated with core platform team to design architecture for new features

Software Developer

July 2012 - August 2015

Fidelity Investments - Westlake, Texas

- Owned and maintained high visibility maturing application dealing with Reference Data Consolidation as well as supported over five other applications within the company's data access layer
- Automated test data setup by incorporating real time data through Java, reducing testing setup time from hours to minutes; this also reduced scripts and manual inputs required to complete E2E integration tests
- Piloted disaster recovery automation efforts, utilized HP Operations Orchestration studio to create release engineering processes to minimize manual inputs and reduce resources on call
- Led integration with vendor-developed IRA to connect to systems for automating data setup, effectively reducing manual setup process from weeks to minutes
- Identified issues with deployment process, learned and implemented UNIX shell scripts to automate deployment process in application environments to reduce deployment errors and overall execution time

INFORMATION

E-Mail arunv4700@gmail.com

Phone (469) 777-0675

Website https://avarghese.me/ng

OPEN SOURCE

Personal Website

My personal website. Utilized Angular 17, Jade, HTML5, Typescript, SCSS, Gulp, Bower, Node, Express, Travis-Cl. Hosted on GitHub!

LATEST PROJECTS

ISC Portal

Angular & Material redesign of customer portal from JSF. Utilized Angular 8, spring boot microservices, various vender APIs, docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins

UBI Pilot

Java micro service architecture redesign to support scaling of reporting abilities for our customer solutions. Building with scalability, resiliency, and distributed computing in mind. Utilized AWS, Kafka, Flink, MySql, Spring Boot, Frisby, Gradle, Docker

Nspire Platform

Groovy/Grails web app used for internal company operations such as warehousing, tier 2 support, problem diagnosis, and migration operations. Utilized linux servers, tomcat app server, MySql, MongoDB, Elastic Search, RabbitMQ, Redis, various vender APIs

SKILLS [Listed by experience level]

Languages

Java/J2EE / JavaScript ES5/ES6 / TypeScript / Shell

Source Control

Github / Bitbucket

Frameworks & Architecture

Agile / Scrum / Micro Services / Spring Boot / REST / SOAP / Hibernate / Event Driven / Domain Driven

Front End

Angular 15+ / NPM / JSON / CSS3 / SCSS / HMTL5

Back End

JPA / MyBatis / Liquibase / Oracle 11g / JDBC

Testing

JUnit / Karma / Jasmine

Build and Automation

Jenkins / Maven / Nexus / Bamboo / Sonar / Ant

Tools

IntelliJ / Eclipse / Postman / SoapUI / Chrome Dev Tools

Data Monitoring

Elastic / Kibana

Interests

ChatGPT / CoPilot / AI / AWS / Kubernetes / Docker

EDUCATION

Graduated May 2012

Bachelor's Degree, Software EngineeringUniversity of Texas at Dallas – Richardson, Texas

ACHIEVEMENTS

US Patent 9491178 B2

Identifying a measure of online security

Published November 2016,

https://www.google.com/patents/US9491178